{"tossups":[{"question":"This word is written on an eagle’s chest in Betye [Betty] Saar’s assemblage Black Girl’s Window. This word is repeated three times next to a mask and the numbers “1, 2, 3” in an “homage to Gertrude Stein” by Charles Demuth. A work prominently featuring this word was inspired by the artist’s childhood attendance at a Christian Science church, and uses a color scheme inspired by the paintings of the artist’s former lover (*) Ellsworth Kelly. This word appeared on a 1965 MoMA Christmas card in a design that was replicated for a 1973 postage stamp whose blue and green background was inspired by what the artist called a “blue Hoosier sky.” For 10 points, a pop art image created by Robert Indiana consists of what word, arranged in a 2-by-2 square with the second letter tilted?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>love<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>love<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"After gaining this status, Jody-Anne Maxwell became a celebrity in her native Jamaica. The Akron reporter Mabel Norris unsuccessfully raised a protest when MacNolia Cox failed to gain this status. After reading the kabbalist Abraham Abulafia, Eliza Baumann abandons her attempt to gain this status in a novel by Myla Goldberg. Both Dylan Chiu and the protagonist attain this status in a 2006 film in which Angela (*) Bassett plays Tanya, the mother of a character played by Keke Palmer. The abandonment of a written tiebreaker led to an unprecedented eight people achieving this status in 2019. In 2021, the basketball prodigy Zaila Avant-garde became the first African American to achieve this status. For 10 points, name this distinction earned at an annual competition sponsored by Scripps.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>winner<\/b><\/u>s of the Scripps (Howard) National <b><u>Spelling Bee<\/b><\/u> [accept synonyms for “winner”]","answer":"<b><u>winner<\/b><\/u>s of the Scripps (Howard) National <b><u>Spelling Bee<\/b><\/u> [accept synonyms for “winner”]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"European Literature","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"A book which attempts to redefine this word notes that, in trying to theorize this concept, we stand “where Bartók’s Judith stands when she asks to open the last door on the night”; that book is George Steiner’s In Bluebeard’s Castle. A quote about this word which has been misattributed to various politicians originates from Hanns Johst’s [yohst’s] play Schlageter [SHLAH-guh-ter]. This word may be described simply as “that which makes life (*) worth living,” and encompasses things like Wensleydale cheese and the Henley Regatta, according to a 1948 attempt to define this word by T. S. Eliot. This word is defined with the phrase “the best which has been thought and said” in a book by Matthew Arnold. For 10 points, name this word defined as “personality writ large” in a Ruth Benedict book titled for its “patterns.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>culture<\/b><\/u> [accept Notes Towards the Definition of <b><u>Culture<\/b><\/u>; accept “When I hear the word <b><u>culture<\/b><\/u>, I reach for my gun”; accept Patterns of <b><u>Culture<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>culture<\/b><\/u> [accept Notes Towards the Definition of <b><u>Culture<\/b><\/u>; accept “When I hear the word <b><u>culture<\/b><\/u>, I reach for my gun”; accept Patterns of <b><u>Culture<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"This language’s longest palindromic word in common use is a 15-letter word for “soap vendor.” An annoying train passenger asks the protagonist of the film Compartment No. 6 to teach him words in this language. This language’s word sisu [SEE-soo], which means something like “tenacity,” is often said to express its country’s national character. This language’s extremely transparent orthography was developed by (*) Mikael Agricola [MEE-kah-el AHG-ree-koh-lah]. This language’s swear word perkele [PAIR-kay-lay] may come from a name for the thunder god Ukko [OOK-koh]. The use of native coinages for scientific words in this language was influenced by Elias Lönnrot [AY-lee-oss LUHN-root], who compiled a national epic in this language about a hero named Väinämöinen [VAA-ee-naa-moy-nayn]. For 10 points, name this language from which English took the word “sauna.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Finnish<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>suomi<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>suomen<\/b><\/u> kieli]","answer":"<b><u>Finnish<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>suomi<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>suomen<\/b><\/u> kieli]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"The Latin translations of this English word and the word “head” were combined by Henry Schoolcraft to coin the name of a lake. The Esperanto translation of this word is the name of a social media app founded by Rafic [rah-feek] Hariri’s son. In some stories, a golem can be deactivated by removing the first letter of the Hebrew translation of this word written on its forehead. This is the standard translation of the Greek word that Martin Heidegger rendered as (*) “unconcealedness,” aletheia [ah-leh-TAY-ah]. The official newspaper of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union was named for the Russian equivalent of both “justice” and this word, pravda [PRAHV-duh]. The Latin translation of this word is the motto of Harvard. For 10 points, name this English translation of the Latin word veritas [VERY-toss].","formatted_answer":"<b><u>truth<\/b><\/u> (Schoolcraft coined the name of Lake Itasca by combining the Latin words veritas and caput, referring to the “true head” of the Mississippi River.)","answer":"<b><u>truth<\/b><\/u> (Schoolcraft coined the name of Lake Itasca by combining the Latin words veritas and caput, referring to the “true head” of the Mississippi River.)","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"In “Finding Out About Children’s Language,” William Labov [luh-BOHV] describes using one of these animals to elicit many more words from children than could be elicited using standard setups. According to a superstition, saying the word for these animals three times on the first day of the month ensures good luck for the rest of the month. The breeding of these animals is called (*) “cuniculture,” which is cognate with a word that is no longer used to describe these animals because of its resemblance to the vulgar word “cunny.” W. V. O. Quine illustrated the inscrutability of reference with the example of someone pointing to one of these animals and saying “gavagai.” These lagomorphs [LAG-uh-morphs] live in systems of burrows called “warrens.” For 10 points, name these relatives of hares.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>rabbit<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>bunny<\/b><\/u> rabbits] (Rabbits were once called “conies,” but the word was superseded by “rabbit” and “bunny” to avoid invoking the taboo word “cunny.”)","answer":"<b><u>rabbit<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>bunny<\/b><\/u> rabbits] (Rabbits were once called “conies,” but the word was superseded by “rabbit” and “bunny” to avoid invoking the taboo word “cunny.”)","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"Justin Martyr’s discussion of this Greek word borrows the ancient use of the adjective spermatikos to modify this noun. Goethe’s [GUR-tuh’s] Faust struggles to translate this word, eventually settling on “deed” as its translation. This Greek word precedes “of God” in the name that the Book of Revelation gives to a heavenly warrior “dressed in a robe dipped in blood.” This word, which the Stoics used to refer to a (*) principle pervading the universe, was identified with Jesus by many early Christian theologians writing about the Johannine [jo-HAN-ine] literature. In the Vulgate, Jerome translates this word as verbum [VAIR-boom]. This Greek word is equated with God at the beginning of the Gospel of John. For 10 points, name this Greek word which can be translated as “reason” or “word.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>logos<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>logos<\/b><\/u> spermatikos]","answer":"<b><u>logos<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>logos<\/b><\/u> spermatikos]","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"This suffix is added to subbóta [suh-BOH-tuh] to refer to Saturdays designated for community volunteer work. This suffix is added to the word chai [chye] to form a word that literally means “teakettle” but which figuratively means a novice computer user. The “o” is stylized as a heart in the name of an online language resource that adds this suffix to the word “word.” A word ending with this suffix refers to Jews who were (*) denied permission to emigrate from the Soviet Union. A Polish word for “worker” that ends in this suffix is also the name of Sonic the Hedgehog’s archenemy. This suffix’s popularity in English was boosted by the 1957 launch of the first artificial satellite. For 10 points, name this suffix that is added to the word “beat” to refer to a person associated with the Beat Generation.","formatted_answer":"-<b><u>nik<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>subbotni<\/b><\/u><b><u>k<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>chainik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Wordnik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>refusenik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Robotnik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Sputnik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>beatnik<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"-<b><u>nik<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>subbotni<\/b><\/u><b><u>k<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>chainik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Wordnik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>refusenik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Robotnik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Sputnik<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>beatnik<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"Early in the pandemic, a member of this band learned Latin on Duolingo and released a Latin-language EP called Roman Songs. This band was challenged to write a song whose lyrics included almost-forgotten words like “limerent” [LIM-uh-rent] and “craniosophic” [cray-nee-oh-SOFF-ik], resulting in their track “Contrecoup” [contra-koo]. This band sang “because it’s extra, baby” about the extra “x” and “y” in the title of their song (*) “S-E-X-X-Y,” the lead single from their album Factory Showroom. This band included the phrases “egad, a base tone denotes a bad age” and “man o nam,” which read the same forwards and backwards, in their song “I Palindrome I.” This band’s album Here Come the ABCs is intended for children learning the alphabet. For 10 points, name this alt-rock band behind “Birdhouse in Your Soul.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>They Might Be Giants<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>TMBG<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>They Might Be Giants<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>TMBG<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"This word can follow “princess” or “madame” to refer to Elizabeth Charlotte, who is the reason why this word can mean a fur cape that covers the shoulders and neck. This is the standard English translation of nádor [NAH-dor], which referred to the highest-ranking Hungarian official besides the king from the 11th century until 1848. This eight-letter word is the second word in a title equivalent to (*) “palsgrave”; in that title, which was held by local rulers who had near-royal powers in the Holy Roman Empire, this word follows “count.” In a two-word title held by people like Charles Louis and the “Winter King” Frederick V, this word follows “elector.” For 10 points, give this word that derives from the name of one of the hills of Rome.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>palatine<\/b><\/u> [accept Princess <b><u>Palatine<\/b><\/u>; accept Madame <b><u>Palatine<\/b><\/u>; accept count <b><u>palatine<\/b><\/u>; accept elector <b><u>palatine<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>palatine<\/b><\/u> [accept Princess <b><u>Palatine<\/b><\/u>; accept Madame <b><u>Palatine<\/b><\/u>; accept count <b><u>palatine<\/b><\/u>; accept elector <b><u>palatine<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"An Iris Murdoch essay ends by saying that, although this word is undefinable, it is connected with “the acceptance of real death”; that essay is titled for the sovereignty of this thing over other concepts. People who “are neither Jesuits, nor democrats, nor even sufficiently Germans” are called this kind of “Europeans” in a book with this adjective in the title. This word is said to be simple in the same way that (*) “yellow” is simple in a book that argues against the “naturalistic fallacy” of trying to define this word reductively, G. E. Moore’s Principia Ethica. The Nicomachean Ethics criticizes Plato’s attempt to define an abstract “form of” this concept. For 10 points, name this word which is the opposite of both “evil” and “bad.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>good<\/b><\/u> [accept “The Sovereignty of <b><u>Good<\/b><\/u> over Other Concepts”; accept <b><u>good<\/b><\/u> Europeans; accept Form of the <b><u>Good<\/b><\/u>] (The second sentence is about Nietzsche’s Beyond Good and Evil.)","answer":"<b><u>good<\/b><\/u> [accept “The Sovereignty of <b><u>Good<\/b><\/u> over Other Concepts”; accept <b><u>good<\/b><\/u> Europeans; accept Form of the <b><u>Good<\/b><\/u>] (The second sentence is about Nietzsche’s Beyond Good and Evil.)","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"Pinastri, the species name of the pine hawkmoth, is used as this type of word in Peter Strickland’s film The Duke of Burgundy. At the climax of the CSI episode “Pirates of the Third Reich,” Grissom uses one of these words which had been taught to him by Lady Heather in an earlier episode. Events like the death of August Ames inspired the founding of the nonprofit (*) Pineapple Support, whose name was inspired by the common use of “pineapple” as this type of word. “Yellow” and “red” are also commonly used as this type of word, including by Christian Grey and Anastasia Steele in the Fifty Shades series. For 10 points, name these words used by BDSM practitioners as signals to stop.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>safe<\/b><\/u>words","answer":"<b><u>safe<\/b><\/u>words","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"A seminal study titled for “classical American” texts of this type was written by the etymologist Allen Walker Read. The German activist Irmela Mensah-Schramm often uses wordplay to alter these texts. A phrase mostly seen in texts of this type was often accompanied by a picture of a man named “Chad,” whose appearance may be based on a (*) circuit diagram. The term “throwie” or “throw-up” refers to a hastily-produced one of these texts. Tracy 168 popularized the term “wildstyle” for a complex, hard-to-read variety of these texts. Texts of this type created during World War II often featured the phrase “Kilroy was here.” For 10 points, name these texts that are called “latrinalia” when they are written in bathroom stalls.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>graffiti<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>graffito<\/b><\/u>; accept Classic American <b><u>Graffiti<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>graffiti<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>graffito<\/b><\/u>; accept Classic American <b><u>Graffiti<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Physics","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"A claim about this word is included in the text data accompanying a 1989 photo of Bob Berry at Arizona’s Red Rock Crossing. In the Strong Bad email called “Website,” Strong Bad hesitates over this word before saying “But you want as many of those as possible.” Upon winning a lifetime achievement award at the 2013 (*) Webbys, a man used his five-word acceptance speech to make a claim about this word. Steve Wilhite, who was part of a team that used this word in a punning slogan about “choosy developers,” has publicly stated that this word was intended to echo the name of a brand of peanut butter. For 10 points, name this image format whose pronunciation is hotly debated online.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>GIF<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>GIF<\/b><\/u>","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"A group from this country is sometimes called the “spinifex [“SPIN-effects”] people” in reference to an endemic grass. In some kinship systems from this country, people are given “skin names” based on which subsection of society they belong to. In many languages from this country, there are distinct sets of words that are used when a man talks with his (*) mother-in-law or a woman talks with her father-in-law. Indigenous people from this country traditionally write words on “message sticks,” often to invite people to events like corroborees [kuh-ROB-uh-reez]. Western anthropologists adapted the Arrernte [AR-un-duh] word alcheringa [al-chuh-RING-guh], referring to this country’s ancestral past, to create the term “the Dreaming.” For 10 points, name this country whose indigenous people include the Torres Strait Islanders and the Aborigines.","formatted_answer":"Commonwealth of <b><u>Australia<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Commonwealth of <b><u>Australia<\/b><\/u>","category":"Religion","subcategory":"Religion","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"The word for this food does not derive from an extremely similar word in the title of a 14th-century cookbook written by “the master cooks of King Richard II.” In South Africa, a “bunny chow” is a hollow loaf of white bread filled with this food. This word coincidentally also refers to a process for converting a multi-argument function into a sequence of single-argument functions, a reference to the namesake of the (*) Haskell language. This word was borrowed into Japanese to refer to a popular dish with pan, udon, and raisu [RICE-oo] varieties. In 2021, Chaheti Bansal called on people to “cancel” this word in a viral Instagram post calling it an “umbrella term popularised by white people.” A Tamil word for “sauce” is the root of, for 10 points, what generic word for any Indian dish with a spiced sauce?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>curry<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>curry<\/b><\/u>ing; accept Haskell <b><u>Curry<\/b><\/u>] (The cookbook is called The Forme of Cury.)","answer":"<b><u>curry<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>curry<\/b><\/u>ing; accept Haskell <b><u>Curry<\/b><\/u>] (The cookbook is called The Forme of Cury.)","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"This author described seeing “the blue blur of bones” after writing a word meaning “family” on a yellow pad in the poem “Logophobia.” This poet described repeatedly writing the letters “a b c” and seeing the fourth letter as a strand of hair on a woman’s cheek in the poem “The Gift,” from a collection that won this author the 2017 T. S. Eliot Prize. This author’s name was inspired by a conversation in which this writer’s mother, who worked as a (*) manicurist, mispronounced the word “beach.” In this author’s 2019 debut novel, Little Dog’s mother is called Rose because her given name, Hong, means “rose” in her native language. For 10 points, name this Vietnamese American author of Night Sky with Exit Wounds and On Earth We’re Briefly Gorgeous.","formatted_answer":"Ocean <b><u>Vuong<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Vương<\/b><\/u> Quốc Vinh]","answer":"Ocean <b><u>Vuong<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Vương<\/b><\/u> Quốc Vinh]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Biology","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"Unusually, this is the only end word in a sestina by Jonah Winter about a motorcycle-riding English professor. A phrase starting with this word may be a reference to the 3rd Marquess of Salisbury’s nepotistic appointment of Arthur Balfour as Chief Secretary for Ireland. A video from the “Chart Party” series ends with the dire prediction that by 2030, the number of professional (*) athletes with this name will have decreased almost to zero; that video is by Jon Bois. This name, which is used to form an acronym and written in all caps in Laura Palmer’s secret diary, refers to the murderous evil spirit from Twin Peaks. This name and Alice are the two most common names given to fictional characters in cryptographic scenarios. For 10 points, name this short form of “Robert.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u> [accept “Sestina: <b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u>”; accept “<b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u>’s your uncle”; “The <b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u> Emergency”; accept Killer <b><u>BOB<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u> [accept “Sestina: <b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u>”; accept “<b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u>’s your uncle”; “The <b><u>Bob<\/b><\/u> Emergency”; accept Killer <b><u>BOB<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"An object studied in knot theory that is analogous to one of these objects, considering only conjugation, is referred to by the nonsense word “quandle.” In an amusing example of Stigler’s law of eponymy, a result stating that the number of orbits is the average number of fixed points of one of these things is sometimes called “the lemma that is not Burnside’s.” The problem of checking whether a sequence of generators represents the identity element of a finitely generated one of these objects is known as the (*) “word problem for” these objects. The Frenchman who coined the word for these algebraic structures died in a duel at the age of 20. For 10 points, Évariste Galois [gal-WAH] coined the name for what structures consisting of a set equipped with a binary operation?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>group<\/b><\/u>s [accept word problem for <b><u>group<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"<b><u>group<\/b><\/u>s [accept word problem for <b><u>group<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"This word replaced a name that was coined by the gold prospector William Dickey. The use of this word was opposed by Ralph Regula, who repeatedly proposed legislation to exploit a loophole preventing the official adoption of this word. In an announcement about the adoption of this word, Sally Jewell said that “40 years is an unreasonable amount of time” to debate the use of this word. This name comes from a (*) Koyukon word meaning “the high one.” In 2015, the Secretary of the Interior announced the adoption of this name, a move which was opposed by many Ohio Republicans but supported by Lisa Murkowski. For 10 points, give this name of North America’s highest mountain, formerly called Mount McKinley.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Denali<\/b><\/u> [reject “Mount McKinley”]","answer":"<b><u>Denali<\/b><\/u> [reject “Mount McKinley”]","category":"Geography","subcategory":"Geography","packetNumber":5,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
